<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The protestatyon of Martin Marprelat wherin not wih [sic] standing the surprizing of the printer, he maketh it known vnto the world that he feareth, neither proud priest, antichristian pope, tiranous prellate, nor godlesse catercap: but defiethe all the race of them by these presents and offereth conditionally, as is farthere expressed hearein by open disputation to apear in the defence of his cause against them and theirs Which chaleng if they dare not maintaine aginst him: then doth he alsoe publishe that he never meaneth by the assitaunce [sic] of god to leaue the a ssayling [sic] of them and theire generation vntill they be vterly extinguished out of our church Published by the worthie gentleman D. martin marprelat D. in all the faculties primat and metropolitan</title>
            <author>Marprelate, Martin, pseud.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07042</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847569</idno>
  <idno type="VID">12607</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240942932</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 17459</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S112314</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99847569e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07042)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12607)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 433:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The protestatyon of Martin Marprelat wherin not wih [sic] standing the surprizing of the printer, he maketh it known vnto the world that he feareth, neither proud priest, antichristian pope, tiranous prellate, nor godlesse catercap: but defiethe all the race of them by these presents and offereth conditionally, as is farthere expressed hearein by open disputation to apear in the defence of his cause against them and theirs Which chaleng if they dare not maintaine aginst him: then doth he alsoe publishe that he never meaneth by the assitaunce [sic] of god to leaue the a ssayling [sic] of them and theire generation vntill they be vterly extinguished out of our church Published by the worthie gentleman D. martin marprelat D. in all the faculties primat and metropolitan</title>
                  <author>Marprelate, Martin, pseud.</author>
                  <author>Throckmorton, Job, 1545-1601, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23 [i.e. 32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Waldegrave?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Wolston, Warks.? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Sept. 1589]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Martin Marprelate has been identified with John Penry and, more probably, with Job Throckmorton.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC and addendum.</note>
                  <note>P. 32 misnumbered 23.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Marprelate controversy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12607:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12607:1"/>
            <p>THE PROTESTATYON OF MARTIN MARPRELAT</p>
            <p>Wherin not wih standing the sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing of the printer, he maketh it known vnto the world that he fear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth, neither proud priest, Antichri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stian pope, tiranous prellate, nor godlesse catercap: but defiethe all the race of them by these presents and offereth conditionally, as is farthere expressed hearein by open disputation to apear in the defence of his cause against them and theirs</p>
            <p>Which chaleng if they dare not maintaine aginst him: then doth he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soe publishe that he never meaneth by the assitaunce of god to leaue the assayl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them and theire generation vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they be vterly extinguised out of our church</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Published</hi> by <hi>the worthie gentleman D. martin mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prelat D. in all the faculties primat and metropolitan</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:12607:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:12607:2"/>
            <head>THE PROTESTACION OF <hi>Martin the great</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Thou canst not lightly bee ignor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunt good reader of that wich hath lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fallen vnto some things of mine, wich were to be printed, or in printing: the presse, leteres, workmen and all, appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended and caried, as male factors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the magistrat, whose authoritie I re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verence, and whose sword I would fear were I as wicked as our Bb are. These events I confes doe strike me, and giue me iuste cause to enter more narrowly into my selfe, to see whethere I bee at peace with god or no: but vtterlye to discouredg me from myne enterpize, a greater matterre then that coms to, I hope shall never be able. The state of the poor men that are taken, I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayle, not becaus thye can hurte mee, for I assure thee they knowe not whoe I am, but in asmuhc as I feare the tirau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny of our wicked pristes, will do that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them wich neithere the worde of god do the warrante, not lawe of the land doth Permitt</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:12607:3"/>
            <p> For as ther hatrede unto the caus is without ground, so ther cruelti to thos that profess the same is withe out measure. Therfore good readere, if thou heere of any mean or compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sionable punishmente inflicte de vpon them (who to say the truth haue deserved non at all, I mean the print ers) I would never haue thee stande to expostulate with our Bb: for this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timly leniti of theirs, for whom I dare take myne other (for I knowe them soe well) that if there fall out any good to those poore men thrughe the provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of god, and the gracious elemen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy of the majestie, they for their parts are no more guilty, or accessary vnto it thē the Spanish unquisitors them selues. For in deed in this one point they are of my mynd vz. That reformatiō can nor well cum to out church withe out bloud. And that noe bloud can hansomely be spilt in that cause, vnlese they them selues be the buchers, and horse leaches to drawe it out. Thou se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est evidently they claim that as a piece
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12607:3"/>and portion of their in heritaunce But tell them from me: that we feare not men who can but kille, the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye: because we feare that god who cā cast both body and soule into vnquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chable fire. And tell them alsoe this. This the more bloode the churche loseth the mor lif and blood it gets When the fearfull sentence pronounc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed against the persecuters of the truth is executed vpon them, I would then gladly know, whether they who go ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ont thus to sheade our bloode: or we whose blood cryeth for vengeance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, shall haue the worst ende of the staffe. We are sure to posses our soules in everlasting peace, when soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver we leav this earthly tabernacle: &amp; in the mean tyme we know: that an haire of our heade can not falle to the grounde without the wil of out heaven lye father: who of his greate mercye loueth vs in, and for our Saviour Crist Iesus, and that with a loue as farr pass<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the loue of a naturall father towarde his children, as he who so loueth vs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excelleth all carthly parents. This per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swation
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12607:4"/>being steadfastly enrgafted in theire harts, who either now or hear-after shalbe trodled for this cause will be a comfort to them in the midest of all their distresses.</p>
            <p>And good reader whosoever thou art I would not haue thee discouraged at this that is latlie fallen out. Resone not frome the successe of thinges vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toe the goodnesse of the causse. For that savourethe too much of the fleashe. yf in be houlding the state of the lowe coutreys, &amp; of Fraunce thou wouldest haue so resoned with thy self thou mightest easylie haue giuen the holye religion of god the slipp 20 yers agoe. Thou must think that in thease successes though they be manye tymes lamentable to the children of god, yet the Lord him selfe hath a specy all hand to trye it maye be who theye are, that with a double face, and who with a siuule hart doe affecte the cause. As to the presente action howsoever ther may escape me some coruption in the handling. Let them be well assured it vas not vndertaken to be intermitted
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12607:4"/>at everye blast of euill successe. Naye let them knowe that by the grace of god the last yeare of <hi>martinisme,</hi> that is, of the discrying and displaying of L Bb shall not be, till full 2 yeas after the last year of <hi>Lambethisme:</hi> that is, so ioyning most godles proceadings vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to to the maintenaunce of an Antichristian and vnlawfull callings in gods churche aginst the knwn truth: for that in deed is righlycaled <hi>Lambethisme</hi> or <hi>Cooperism</hi> chuse you whether.</p>
            <p>And be it knowne vnto them that <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinisme</hi> stands vpon an other maner of fundat on, then ther prelacy doth or can stand. Therofe yf they will needs ouerthrowe me, let them goe in hand with the exdloyte, rather by proov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the lawfullnes of their places: then by exercising the force of ther vnlawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full tyranny. For one again I feare not ther tyranny. And one sound syllogism (wich I tell you is dainty ware in a bish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opes breast) brought in for the poofe of their vnlawfull callings, shall more dismay &amp; sooner enduce me to giue over my course then a thousand warāts a thousad pursevants, a thousand threts
<pb facs="tcp:12607:5"/>and a thousand racks wich course be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they take not, therefore all theire other drifts, &amp; devises are to non othere end, then to shewe the greate care and skilie they haue to carye awaye all the blowes but what get they by thertiran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye: seeing it is truth and not violence that most vphoulde their places? Doe they not knowe that the more violence they vse, the more breath they spende. And what wisdome were this trowe ye for a man that had coursed him selfe windlesse, to atempt the recoverye of his breath by running vp, and downe to find ayre? So you know he might soon haue as much life in his members, as L Bb haue relligion and conscience in their proceedings.</p>
            <p>The whol issu of ther forc &amp; bloodthur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stie attemptes doth nothing els but wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes againste them that they are the chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren of those fathers, who neuer as yet durst abide to haue their proceedings examined by the word, and me thinks they should be ashamede to haue it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordede vnto ages to come, that they haue evere shuned to meintaine theyre cause, eithere by open disputation, or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12607:5"/>or by any other sounde conference or writing. Let me be ouerthrown by any of these wayes, and I doe here by these my writings publikly protest, that I wil neuer molest L. bishopp againe while I liue, but wil with very great vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, to the vttermost of my endeuour, maintain them and their cause, as euer I did oppugne the same; otherwise I do with the like constancie and resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion protest, that by the aide and assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of God, I wil neuer leaue the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playing of them and their proceedings vntil they bee made as odious in our Churche and common wealth, as that they be thought of al sorts, vnworthie to be hardoured therein.</p>
            <p>And this offer of mine so reasonable and in euery respect so easie to be yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto, if they refuse; who seeth not therein a secrete implying, and a close graunting of the desperatnesse and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serie of their cause? which shaketh and quiuereth, and shrinketh as it were, in <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he sinowes, to thinke that there shold <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e any buckling towardes; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore doth wisely shift of all honest and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12607:6"/>lawfull meanes of triall, as hauing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to vpholde it, but tyrannie and blood.</p>
            <p>Nowe because they woulde gladly know Martin, I wil here set them down a waye, whereby they maye not onely know him, but (that which is more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull vnto them; they may quench their thirst with his blood if they wil:) prouided that they bee able to make their cause good against him by the worde of God.</p>
            <p>I doe therefore by this my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation, make it knowne to the whole church of England, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally vnto our magistrats, more espe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially vnto our gracious soveraign, and vnto al posterities to com, that I who do now go vnder the name of Martin Marprelate, do offer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonally to apear, and there to make my self knowen in open disputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vpon the danger, not onlie of my libertie but also of my life, to maintaine against all our bishops
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12607:6"/>or any els whosoever, that shal dare in any Scholastical manner, to take their parts: the cause of the church government, which is now in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversie betwixt me and our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats: so that I may have this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion following inviolablie kept &amp; obserued, vz. That for appearing, or for anye thinge that I haue eyther published or caused to be publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this cause, I be not delt with, or molested, except thei overthrow me by the worde of God, which if they doe, confusion be vpon me if I doe not yeelde. But if in this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter I overthrowe them (as I make no question of it, if they dare abide the pushe) then they to trusse vp and be packing to ROME, &amp; to trouble our church no longer. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided also, that if any of the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes wil ioyn with me, &amp; venture their liues in the cause, it maye be lawfull for them to come in freely
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12607:7"/>against these dragons in disputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>I call thee here againe (good reader) to witness the indifferencie of my chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge and offer, and to iudge what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counte thou oughtest to make of our present Church-gouernement by lord archbishops and bishops, vpon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusall of the former condition by thē; and whether thervpon, I may not iust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and lawfully proclaime the victorie ouer them in manner following.</p>
            <p>Be it knowne vnto all states, Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and Vniversities vnder heauen; and vnto all men, eyther present or to come, of what estate or condition soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: that in asmuch as M. Fenners, &amp; M. Penties syslogismes, whereby Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor Bridges his booke is confuted, and the cause of reformation vnanswerably prooued. M. Trauers, M. Cartwrights, &amp; M. Gilbyes, the Demonstration of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scipline, the Abstract, the Counterpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, M. Tindall, M. Frith, M. Barnes, M. Hooper, M. Pilkington, M. Foxe, and M. Martin Marprelates writinges, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with other learned discourses
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12607:7"/>mo; whereby the corruption, and the vnlawfulnes of the places, and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of L. bishops, are shamefully laide open vnto the worlde, are as yet vnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered; and likely to be no otherwise confuted, then with slanders, ribaldry scurrillity, reuiling, imprisonment, and torture: and inasmuche, as they dare not maintaine their cause against mee by open and publike disputation; that therefore they doe manifestly confesse their cause and procedings to be clean foild, ouerthrown, and made euen with the grounde, in suche sorte, as beside whorish impudencie, halter, axe, bonds scourging and racking, with suche o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther weapons, as were bequeathed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them by their forefathers, the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient enemies and persecutors of the Churche, they haue not left any instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to defend themselues.</p>
            <p>And let thē be sure, seeing they dare come to no lawfull way of try all with me, that there shall not be ap post in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great streete or place of concourse, almost in the lande, but I will make an affixe; and set vp this my foresaide de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12607:8"/>of the victorie hadde ouer them, to their shame: and I will also make forraine nations ring of their vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies and vngodlines, if the publishing of their doings in latine can doe it.</p>
            <p>And as for my self, my life, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer els I possesse, I haue long agone set vp my rest, making that account of it, as in standing against the enemies of God, and for the libertie of his church it is of no value in my sight. My life in this cause shalbe a gayne to the church, and no losse to my selfe, I knowe right well: and this is al the reckning which by the assistance of the lord I wil make as long as I liue, of al the tormēts they haue deuised for me. I am blamed of many in this mine attempt, not onely for throwing my selfe into great daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; but also for the vtter vndoing of my wife and children. I do thanke thē with all my hearte, for their care ouer those poore soules, and commend thē for their secresie and wisdome, that in knowing my wife and my childrē, they haue not by shewin their vnmeasura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble loue towards them, discouered me
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12607:8"/>You see what it is when wise men haue the handlinge of a matter. I perceine if these men were not verye prouident and warie, that Martin could not bee long vnknowne. For I tel you, if a mans wife and children be once knowne, it is not possible that he can be secret a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny long time; and yet me thinkes, that all their wisdome, and al their care o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer my wife and children whē the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is wel wayed, is scant woorth three strawes. For what if Martin had ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wife nor childe in all his life, are they not then something too much o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wayned in their owne conceit, who giue out, that he hath both. Wil you beleeue me then if I tel you the truth? to put you therefore out of all doubt, I may safely protest vnto you with a good conscience, that howsoeuer the speech may seeme strange vnto many, yet the very truth is, that hitherto I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer had wife nor childe in all my life: not that I neuer meane to haue anye; for it may be, notwithstanding all the rage and barkinge of the Lambethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall whelpes, I may be married, &amp; that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12607:9"/>ere it belong.</p>
            <p>For me thinks this should be inough that two onely of the Metropolitanes of the lande, shoulde continue mayden (though I feare scarce virgine) priestes. But whensoeuer I am maried, it would do me good at the heart, to see a dozen of good and honest L. bishops daunce at my wedding, sauing that as M. Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall hath verye well noted, Practize of Prelates, page 374. It is not possible na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally, there should be any good and honest L. bishopp. Well, howsoeuer it goes with me, you see howe little cause as yet, my wife and children haue to feare that antichrist of Lambeth &amp; his instruments.</p>
            <p>To omitte these matters, will they know indeede why I feare them not, &amp; wherefore they ought not to terrifie thee (good reader, if the Lord hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed vpon thee the same minde that he hath vouchsafed mee?) Why surely it is, because they against whom I deal, haue so prouoked the anger of God, and the prayers of his Churche against thē, as stand lōg they cannot; if eyther
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12607:9"/>lord be true of his promise, or the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Churche made in sayth; can be hearde. Of both which I make no question. Hereunto you may ad, that I feare them not, inasmuche as the ende wherefore I haue taken this worke in hand, was onely the glory of God, by deliuering of his Churche, from the great tyrannie and bondage, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with these tyranntes doe oppresse the same. I delt not herin, as the Lord kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, because I woulde please my selfe or my reader, in a pleasant vain of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. If that bee the thing I sought or seek after; then let my writings be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the graue of all proud prelates; that is, neuer mentioned in the church of God without detestation. Euen so was it as farr from mee that by sharpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning my penne against them, I shoulde thereby (as some foolishely giue out) make away for my selfe, or other great men vnto their liuinges and promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For if the possession and enioying of a good conscience but for one day alone, be not more deare to me then all their vngodly pompe, and ambici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12607:10"/>preheminence; then let mine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries prey vpon me, and let my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward be nothing else, but the very bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternesse of their malicious heartes. I haue I thanke God of mine own, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I am better content, then they are, with all their spoile and robberie. And if I wanted, I coulde tell howe to liue in an honest calline, with better credit in the Churche of God, then all the L. byshopps of England doe: and I may safely saye, it is so far from me, to bringe the Churche liuinges into the hands of any but the ministers, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers thereof; that I can no more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide Church-robberie in a temporall man, then I can brooke sacriledge in a presumptuous priest: as I hate the on, so I abhorre the other.</p>
            <p>But as concerninge the laying open of their bishopprickes to the spoyle of such cormorāts as gape for their down fals, thereby only to enrich themselues I greatly muze, that our prelates wil be so ouersene as to charge me therwith. For it is well knowne, that none of thē all, no not the proudest prieste in the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12607:10"/>lande, doth so cumber himselfe, in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring how he should liue that comes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him: but that now al of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin pretily, either of their wonted loue to themselues, or of ther natural spight to their successors; to take such chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table order, as that if they maye haue their wils, I hope ther shal not be much left in a while, to allure anye couetous Courtier to the spoile. Wherein, no dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prayse to any, I must needs commende for their forecast in this pointe, a cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of as arrant bishops (for it were pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to bereaue the deuil of his due com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mendation) as anye the land yeeldeth. The men, or rather beasts that I mean, are Iohn London, and Thomas Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chester: whereof the one at Fulham, the other by Whitney in Oxfordshire; haue so contended in throwing down Elmes, as if the wager had bene, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them shoulde most haue impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerished their bishoppricks. And yet I blame not Mar-Elme, so much as Coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for this facte: because it is no lesse giuen him by his name to spoil elmes, then it is allotted him by the secrete
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12607:11"/>iudgement of God to mar the church. Whereas a man of M. Coopers age, &amp; occupation, so wel seene n that trade, might easily knowe, that tubs made of greene timber, must needs leake out of al cry. And yet now I consider with my selfe; I do not so greatly maruell at the matter: For he that makes no consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to be a deceiuer, and a false pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in the buildinge of the Churche; will not sticke for his gaine, to be a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceifull workeman in making of tubbs.</p>
            <p>Well, concerning the care that our prelates haue, in leauing of this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoouefull for their successours. I may truely saye, that were it not more for feare of law than for any conscience of the maintenance of the ministerie; the whol bishoppricke, euen to day before to morowe, woulde not yeelde a L. by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop so much, as might purchase him an handsome halter to hang himselfe with, as the Poet sayth. Therefore let them neuer taulke more for shame (as their <hi>T.C</hi> doth) of the care they haue that the churches maintenance should not decay. And as herein their spoile &amp;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12607:11"/>robbery is apparant; on the other side; So their tyrannie and blood thirstie proceedinges against good men, is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excusable.</p>
            <p>And as herein their spoile and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berie is apparent, so on the other side their tyrannie and blood thirstie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings is vnexcusable: and yet is the maner of their proceedings more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable and dangerous to the state, then their very practises themselues.</p>
            <p>Firste you see they maye examine of what they will. For who can let them; when they be both sole iudges, &amp; sole witnesse themselues, &amp; none other by, but the poore examinate. To which effecte, what is the seate of iustice they commonly vse in these cases, but onely some close chamber at Lambeth, or some obscure gallerie in London pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace? where according to the true na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of an euill conscience, that flyeth and feareth the light; they may iuggle &amp; foyst in what they list without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolment; and so attempt (if they wil) to enduce the partie examined, to be of a conspiracie with them, to pull
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12607:12"/>the crowne off her Maiesties head. And I put case they shoulde doe so (as here you see is a way laid open for them, to broach any conspiracie in the worlde) what remedie shoulde the partie that stands there alone haue, by apeaching or complayning? any other trowe you then this: he lyes like a puritan knaue; ile haue his eares; ile haue the <hi>scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum magnatum</hi> against him: For he hath slaundered the hight commission, and the president of her Maiesties councel; Namely, my L. of Canterburies wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship? and here behold the poore mans reward.</p>
            <p>Secondly, you must lay you hand on the booke, and not knowe whereunto you must be sworn: yea, they be so ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest, that they will compell you to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse your selfe, or els you shall lye by it; which vngodly practise of theirs, sauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth so ranckly of the Spanishe inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that it is flatt contrarye to all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie, the expresse lawes of the land, and the doctrine of our Churche. For the law is so far from compelling anye to appeache himselfe in a cause where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12607:12"/>in eyther life, goods, or good name is called in question, that it altogether condemneth those for oppressours of the common libertie of her Maiesties subiectes; and for vnreasonable viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and wresters of all good order of iustice; that will vrge or require anye such thing at their hands, as may more at large appeare in a plaine Statute of the 25, of Hen. 8. in the tytle of heresie. And therefore men maye see what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counte they ought to make of those shamelesse speeches of that woorthye gray head, Mistresse Coopers husband: who as he hath bene long since, to old to blushe; so did he not let, openly to avouche; That before God, there was noe other waye of tryall, nor no state could stand and continue without it.</p>
            <p>To conclude this point. It is too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest, that 1. by these their priuate whisperinge examinations in corners, 2. by the othe thus administred at randome; 3 by the enforcing of men to accuse them-selues. Our byshopps with their wretched fauourers, may in time (as it is not vnlikely but they wil)
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12607:13"/>bring one of these mischienous incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences vpon her Maiesties best sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects: vz. eyther perpetuall imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, losse of eares or some other lim: or els (as I said before) an enforcement to conspire the overthrowe of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties crowne and dignitie. Whether these matters be not worthie the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of the grauest councellors in the land, I leaue it to the iudgement of euery true Englishman that loueth his Prince and the libertie of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. But Martin is an intoller able busie fellowe, for molesting the state of the cleargie in this sort.</p>
            <p>Now I hastē to other matters, where it may be, good Reader, thou wilt aske what was in that Pistle of mine? To tel thee true, I sigh to remember the losse of it, it was so prettie, and so witty. And I know if thou hadst it, thou wouldest laye it vp, among other thy honest re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations for thy delight.</p>
            <p>Firste then, there was set downe for thy learning; the true, proper, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall definition, or rather description of Martinisme, to this effect. That to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12607:13"/>be a right Martiniste indeede, is to bee neither Browniste, Cooperist, Lambe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thist, Schismatike, Papist, atheist, traytor nor yet L. byshop; but one that is at de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyaunce with all men; whether he bee French, Ducth, Spanish, Catercap, pope or popeling, so far forth as he is an eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to God and her Maiestie. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon I remember, I did then aske the reader, whether it were not good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Martiniste: and as I did then, so do I still heartely reioyce to think that all the honestest, and best affected sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects her Maiestie hath, will one day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Martinists.</p>
            <p>Then among al the rimers and stage plaiers, which my Ll. of the cleargy had suborned against me. I remember Mar-Martin, Iohn a Cant. his hobbie-horse, was to his reproche, newly put out of the Morris, take it how he will; with a flat discharge for euer shaking his shins about a May-pole againe while he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Here-abouts I placed D. Vnderhil and D. Wood of Alsolne colledge, to be chaplaines vnto a certain chaste Fic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of Hell, called sir Iames King, of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12607:14"/>Harford-shire; and some-where it was, that I so sliued Dick Bancroft ouer the shulders, as his chaplainship is neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to recouer his credite, if that Pistle of mine be once published. Nexte to this (as I take it) followed a preamble to an Eblitaph vpon the death of olde Andrewe Turne-coate, to be song anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonically in his graces Chappell, on wednesdayes and Frydayes, to the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable tune of Orawhynemeg.</p>
            <p>Then was there a certaine vulnerall Sermon of olde Lockwood of Sarum, vpon the sodaine and vntimely death of his saide brother Pearne, wherein he did vndertake for him, that he was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer puritane in his life, but alwayes an orderly man, and a maintainer of the state of the cleargie.</p>
            <p>And if his grace did appoint anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to preach at his old good masters funeralls, but onely this quick-witted Bridges, he was certainly fowly ouer-seene. For there would haue bene such a messe, and such a match, such a payre of saints, the one liuing, and the other deade; as I beleeue the Legend-aure
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12607:14"/>woulde not yeelde the like: both olde standardes, both proculstants, both ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercaps, both priests, both deans, both hypocrites, both asses: why sans mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie said I, &amp;c. but alas, chaue haulfe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten the rest.</p>
            <p>After this, I had a fling at these puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes, concerning whome, my desire is, that wherein I am faltie, ye puritanes would set me downe the particulars. It is odds, I shall some way or other heare of it. For albeit there haue bene some iarres of vnkindnesse betwixt vs, yet I would haue you know, that I take the worst of you, in regarde of his calling, to be an honester man, then the best L. bishop in christendom. The report go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that some of you haue preached a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst me, and I beleeue it in part; well looke to it, for I may happen be euen with you in this manner: I will not rest till I haue learned what it is that yee haue said of me; and if I finde it to be a iust reproofe, I will mend my falt, be as angrie as ye will: if vniuste, trust vnto it, I will holde on my course, and there is one rappe more then ye looked for.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:12607:15"/>
            <p> The next prettie thing to this, was to my remembrance, Chaplain Some con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed with the balde sheath of his own dagger, wherein al his short cuts, latine Apothegs, and childishe Pen-an-inke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne prouerbes, were wholly inuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon himselfe. I then said, &amp; so say I still, that if it were not for those whom our bishopps hate and persecute, it is knowne they would make a mad piece of confuting of the Brownisses and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sectaries amongest them: as may appeare by that whiche they suffer to come out so nakedly, and patchedly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, by this father Robert of theirs. And this is he that hath crazed his braine at Lambeth, and his consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence at Gyrton; whose balde writings without sappe or edge, vnworthye of a boye of 12. yeare olde; haue (I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded) made and will make (if it bee not looked vnto) more Brownistes in our church, then al that euer they haue hitherto published themselues.</p>
            <p>This (if you know him not) is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye same Doctor, that in publishing 3. prettie treatises, hath so handled the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12607:15"/>matter, by a Geometricall dimension, that the last (if it be well scanned) is the same with the first, &amp; the middlemost, all one with them both: the man in all likelihoode, neuer goeth without a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle saunce-bell in his pocker; and that doth nothing els but <hi>Ting, Ting, Ting;</hi> and what doth it <hi>Ting?</hi> if you giue good eare, nothing els I warrant you; but My sermons, My writings, My reasons, My arguments; &amp; al is My, My, My; as if the depth of all learning, were included in the chanell of his braine. This is euen he, that let him write as many books as he will (thogh he should neuer so much disguise himselfe, &amp; conceale his name) yet we should be sure to knowe him by one of these rapping figures; Eyther by hittinge the white, or by missinge the Butt; or by Resting on his reason; or by 32. dozen of full points; or by som such broken wooden dishe or other.</p>
            <p>Then was there recorded a braue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement which martin of his curtesie is contented to make with the bishops, whiche agreement was taught once in the pulpit, by a certaine lame Ficker of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12607:16"/>Warwicke, a chaplaine of their owne stampe. His text was out of Matthewe; <hi>agree with thine aduersarie quicklie.</hi> Wee haue an aduersarie said he, who is that? the Diuell; how shall we agree with the Diuell? euen thus said he, and if you marke it is a good lesson: Shake him off, neuer come nigh him, nor haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doe with him. Euen so, ile bee bounde that my selfe, and all the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans shall agree with the byshops while the worlde standes; on this condition, that we shake thē off, neuer come nigh them, nor haue nothing to doe with them.</p>
            <p>Twere pity to forget Martins <hi>Tolbooth</hi> in the middest wherof, were many rare conceits; as a great asshen chaire, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Iohn a Bridges was placed by patent during his life; and Leonarde Wright appointed to keepe it cleane, by scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and rubbing the feet of it; Round aboute this Tolboothe, were placed a foule ranke of Catercaps, conferring &amp; disputing hotly, about the thirde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clension, the churching of women, or such like matters of life and death. On
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12607:16"/>the first fourm, sate in ranke, Iohn, Iohn and William; on the seconde. Richard, Richard, and Thomas; on a third, Iohn William and Marmaduke, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>After this followed some-thing, a large confutation of Friar Freguevil, &amp; of wringlefaced Wrighte; within which compsse, were contayned, 1 a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest proof, that reformation importeth the ouerthrow of the state of the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, &amp; that according vnto the doctrine of our church: 2 an antithesis between our Sauiour Christ, &amp; that cursed pope of Lambeth, Iohn Whitgift: 3 a proof of many of those theses which that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie boye of mine published so vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timelye: but as for him and his elder brother, together with that blinde asse Pasquill, I will haue them talked with elswhere: with these &amp; such like points with an honourable mention of all no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble souldiors; a complaint of the losse of my papers, and the miserie of sea iournies I ended my Pistle, being the first Tome of more warke for the Coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. And here also I end this my prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>station. Desiring thee (good reader) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinng
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12607:17"/>vnto thy place, to be carefull of the reliefe and deliuerance of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresled printers. In requitall whereof, if thou canst but learne the day of my marriage (for as I protested vnto thee without all fraud and ambiguitie, I was neuer as yet married in my life) thou shalt be better welcome vnto me, then the best Lord Catercap of them all, and so tell them from me when thou wilt.</p>
            <p>Page 6. line 23. read single for siuule, page 21. there is some-thing twise set downe, mend that thy selfe if thou wilt, for I promise thee I cannot. Yet heare me a word afore thou goest, an thou be a goodfellow, commend me to George Bullen Deane of Liechfield, by these 4, tokens: 1 The wind is south, the wind is south: 2. that he lately taught in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventree, that men might fal from grace 3 that taking himselfe with a fault in the same sermon, he said, there I lyed there I lyed 4 being at another time in the pulpit, hearing his dogg cry, he out with this text; <hi>whie how now hoe, can you not let my dogg alone there; come</hi> Springe <hi>come</hi> Spring.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12607:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>